{
  "reference_number": "2407",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "We should aim for a negative level of long-lived gases. New Zealand should have at least the forestry potential to pursue this goal,\n and may well be a great place for marine permaculture as well. I also support a science-based approach to ensure we have the most\n impactful ways of reducing emissions."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Carbon Dioxide - Reducing net carbon dioxide emissions to zero by 2050",
      "answer_index": 13,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": "I would like to seriously qualify my answer - it is not clear that any present international units would truly meet strong environmental\n\n safeguards. Using international credits should come with commensurate increases in ambition of targets (eg looking to negative\n emissions). The New Zealand government should itself be able to verify the credibility of any international units."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Any change should have to be by new legislative change - I read this as allowing an alteration by the Minister alone. If changes are\n\n allowed, the criteria for this should be clearly set out as only including major changes in scientific knowledge or international\n agreements. Economic changes should not be enough - this would undermine the credibility of the target."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I agree that the Government and the Climate Commission should take the following factors into consideration when advising on and\n\nsetting budgets: • scientific knowledge regarding climate change • technology relevant to climate change • economic\ncircumstances and the likely impact of a decision on the economy, as well as the competitiveness of particular sectors of the\n\neconomy • fiscal circumstances and the likely impact of the decision on taxation, public spending and public borrowing • social\ncircumstances and the likely impact of a decision on fuel poverty • energy policy and the likely impact of a decision on energy\n\nsupplies and the carbon and energy intensity of the economy."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "This is absolutely critical, otherwise the obligations to meet targets are avoidable. For most people, the actual policies required to\nmeet targets will mean the most. I also believe the Act should include a clear accountability mechanism where plans are set out that\n\nwill not meet budgets. I would support an option that created a statutory framework for judicial review of plans. This could either be\nopen review allowing judicial review of plans that will not meet targets (and therefore fail to meet the government's obligations), or\n\notherwise review if the government cannot justify a deviation from the recommendations of the Climate Change Commission."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The Government’s policy plans to meet emission budgets should be comprehensive, fair, cost-effective, environmentally sustainable,\nand reflect a commitment to Te Tiriti o Waitangi. The government should specifically have to consider the longer-term implications of\n\nthe plans, so that it has to justify any situation where it is relying on later emissions reductions rather than sooner. It should also have\nto clearly specify exact emissions reductions from policies in the plan, so that it is clear that the plan meets the budget."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I agree with the following collective expertise: • climate change policy (including emissions trading) • resource economics and\n\nimpacts (including social impacts, labour markets and distribution) • te Tiriti o Waitangi, te reo me ona tikanga Māori and Māori\ninterests • climate and environmental science including mātauranga Māori • experience with addressing adaptation challenges like\nplanning, insurance and local government • risk management • engineering and/or infrastructure • community engagement and\n\ncommunications. • business competitiveness • knowledge of the public and private innovation and technology development system.\nI think expertise in public health is also important. Knowledge of agriculture could also be useful."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I agree with the proposed functions below, but recognise that nuance is required in terms of how local councils are involved: • a\nnational climate change risk assessment • a national adaptation plan • regular review of progress towards implementing the national\n\nadaptation plan • an adaptation reporting power"
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I am a qualified New Zealand lawyer with a Masters Degree in Environmental and Energy Law from New York University. I am 27 years\nold and will see substantial impacts of climate change in my lifetime. I think it is important that in addition to setting targets and plans,\n\nNew Zealand indicates its real present commitment to taking action on climate change, by introducing a functional price on carbon. A\nZero Carbon Act could be passed to include a set of current policies to help reduce emissions straight away, and the credibility of the\n\nlaw would be boosted if we saw action being taken right away.\n\n\n\n You have elected to withhold your personal details from publication."
    }
  ]
}
